Chapter 61.
Stub kills a whale.
If to Starbucks the apparition of the squid was a thing of portance, to
Quiquake it was quite a different object.
When you see him quidd, said the savage, honing his harpoon in the bow of his
hoisted boat, then you quick see him farm whale.
The next day was exceedingly still and sultry, and with nothing special to
engage them, the Peekquad's crew could hardly resist the spell of sleep induced
by such a vacant sea. For this part of the Indian Ocean through which we were
voyaging is not what whalemen call a lively ground. That is, it affords fewer
glimpses of porpuses, dolphins, flying fish, and other vivaceious denisonons of
more stirring waters than those off the Rio de la Plata or the inshore ground off Peru.
It was my turn to stand at the foreast head, and with my shoulders leaning
against the slackened royal shrouds, to and fro I idally swayed in what seemed
an enchanted air. No resolution could withstand it. In that dreamy mood,
losing all consciousness, at last my soul went out of my body, though my body
still continued to sway as a pendulum will, long after the power which first
moved it is withdrawn.
air forgetfulness altogether came over me. I had noticed that the seammen at
the mine and misenmast heads were already drowsy, so that at last all
three of us lifelessly swung from the spars, and for every swing that we made,
there was a nod from below from these slumbering helmsmen. The waves too
nodded their indolent crests, and across the wide trance of the sea, east nodded
to west, and the sun overall.
Suddenly bubbles seemed bursting beneath my closed eyes. Like vices, my hands
grasped the shrouds. Some invisible gracious agency preserved me. With a
shock, I came back to life. And low, close under our lee, not 40 fathoms off,
a gigantic sperm whale lay rolling in the water like the cap-sized hull of a
frigot, his broad, glossy back of an Ethiopian hue, glistening in the sun's
rays like a mirror, but lazily undulating in the trough of the sea, and
ever in a non-tranquily spouting his vapory jet, the whale looked like a
portly burger smoking his pipe of a warm afternoon. But that pipe, poor whale,
was thy last. As if struck by some enchanter's wand, the sleepy ship, and
every sleeper in it, all at once started into wakefulness, and more than a score
of voices from all parts of the vessel, simultaneously, with the three notes
from a loft, shouted forth the accustomed cry, as the great fish slowly
and regularly spouted the sparkling brine into the air.
Clear away the boats. Luff, cried Ahab, and obeying his own order, he dashed the
helm down before the helmsman could handle the spokes.
The sudden exclamations of the crew must have alarmed the whale, and air the
boats were down majestically turning, he swam away to the lured. But with such a
steady tranquility, and making so few ripples as he swam, that thinking, after
all, he might not as yet be alarmed, Ahab gave orders that not an ore should
be used, and no man must speak but in whispers. So seated like Ontario Indians
on the gunnels of the boats, we swiftly but silently paddled along, the calm not
admitting of the noiseless sails being set. Presently, as we thus glided in
chase, the monster perpendicularly flitted his tail 40 ft into the air, and
then sank out of sight like a tower swallowed up. There go flukes, was the
cry, an announcement immediately followed by stubs producing his match
and igniting his pipe, for now a respit was granted. After the full interval of
his sounding had elapsed, the whale rose again, and being now in advance of the
smoker's boat, and much nearer to it than any of the others, Stub counted
upon the honor of the capture. It was obvious now that the whale had at length
become aware of his pursuers. All silence of cautiousness was therefore no
longer of use. Paddles were dropped and or oars came loudly into play, and still
puffing at his pipe, Stub cheered on his crew to the assault.
Yes, a mighty change had come over the fish. All alive to his jeopardy, he was
going head out, that part obliquely projecting from the mad yeast which he brewed.
Footnote. It will be seen in some other place of what a very light substance the
entire interior of the sperm whale's enormous head consists, though
apparently the most massive, it is by far the most buoyant part about him, so
that with ease he elevates it in the air, and invariably does so when going
at his utmost speed. beside such as the breadth of the upper part of the front
of his head, and such the tapering cutwater formation of the lower part,
that by obliquely elevating his head, he thereby may be said to transform himself
from a bluff bowed, sluggish galli into a sharpointed New York pilot boat. End of footnote.
Starter, starter, my men, don't hurry yourselves. Take plenty of time, but
start her. Start her like thunder claps that's all cried Stub spluttering out
the smoke as he spoke. Start her now.
Give him the long and strong stroke Tash Tego. Starter Tash my boy. Start her all
but keep cool. Keep cool. Cucumbers is the word. Easy. Easy. Only starter like
grim death and grinning devils. And raise the buried dead perpendicular out
of their graves. boys. That's all.
Starter.
Woohoo. Why he screamed the gay header in reply, raising some old war whoop to
the skies, as every orarsman in the strained boat involuntarily bounced
forward with the one tremendous leading stroke which the eager Indian gave. But
his wild screams were answered by others quite as wild. Kihei he yelled Dagu
straining forwards and backwards on his seat like a pacing tiger in his cage.
Kala kulu howled Quequ as if smacking his lips over a mouthful of grenaders
stake and thus with orars and yells the kees cut the sea. Meanwhile, Stub,
retaining his place in the van, still encouraged his men to the onset, all the
while puffing the smoke from his mouth.
Like desperados, they tugged and they strained till the welcome cry was heard.
Stand up, Tashego. Give it to him. The harpoon was hurled. Stern all. The
oresman backed water. The same moment something went hot and hissing along
every one of their wrists. It was the magical line. An instant before Stub had
swiftly caught two additional turns with it round the loggerhead, whence, by
reason of its increased rapid circlings, a hemp and blue smoke now jetted up and
mingled with the steady fumes from his pipe. As the line passed round and round
the logger head, so also just before reaching that point, it blisteringly
passed through and through both of Stub's hands, from which the handcloths,
or squares of quilted canvas, sometimes worn at these times, had accidentally
dropped. It was like holding an enemy's sharped two-edged sword by the blade,
and that enemy all the time striving to rest it out of your clutch.
Wet the line. Wet the line," cried Stub, to the tub oresman, him seated by the
tub, who, snatching off his hat, dashed seaater into it.
Footnote: Partly to show the indispensibleness of this act, it may
here be stated that in the old Dutch fishery, a mop was used to dash the
running line with water. In many other ships, a wooden pigan or bor is set
apart for that purpose. Your hat, however, is the most convenient." End of footnote.
More turns were taken so that the line began holding its place. The boat now
flew through the boiling water like a shark, all fins, stub and tachego here
changed places, stem for stern. A staggering business truly in that rocking commotion.
From the vibrating line extending the entire length of the upper part of the
boat, and from its now being more tight than a harpstring, you would have
thought the craft had two keels, one cleaving the water, the other the air,
as the boat churned on through both opposing elements at once. A continual
cascade played at the boughs, a ceaseless whirling eddy in her wake, and
at the slightest motion from within, but even of a little finger, the vibrating,
cracking craft caned over her spasmotic gunnel into the sea. Thus they rushed,
each man with might and man clinging to his seat to prevent being tossed to the
foam and the tall form of Tashego at the steering ore crouching almost double in
order to bring down his center of gravity. Whole Atlantics and Pacific
seemed past as they shot on their way till at length the whale somewhat slackened his flight.
Haul in, haul in, cried Stub to the bowsman, and facing round towards the
whale, all hands began pulling the boat up to him, while yet the boat was being
towed on. Soon ranging up by his flank, Stub, firmly planting his knee in the
clumsy cleat, darted dart after dart into the flying fish, at the word of
command, the boat alternately sterning out of the way of the whale's horrible
wallow, and then ranging up for another fling.
The red tide now poured from all sides of the monster, like brooks down a hill.
His tormented body rolled not in brine, but in blood, which bubbled in sea for
furlongs behind in their wake. The slanting sun playing upon this crimson
pond in the sea sent back its reflection into every face, so that they all glowed
to each other like red men. And all the while, jet after jet of white smoke was
agonizingly shot from the spiracle of the whale, and vehement puff after puff
from the mouth of the excited headsman, as at every dart, hauling in upon his
crooked lance by the line attached to it, Stub straightened it again and again
by a few rapid blows against the gunnel, and then again and again sent it into
the whale. "Pull up! Pull up!" he now cried to the bowsman as the waning whale
relaxed in his wrath. "Pull up close, too." And the boat ranged along the
fish's flank. When reaching far over the bow, Stub slowly churned his long, sharp
lance into the fish, and kept it there, carefully, churning and churning, as if
cautiously, seeking to feel after some gold watch that the whale might have
swallowed, and which he was fearful of breaking air he could hook it out. But
that gold watch he sought was the innermost life of the fish. And now it
is struck. For starting from his trance into that unspeakable thing called his
flurry, the monster horribly wallowed in his blood, overwrapped himself in
impenetrable, mad boiling spray, so that the imperiled craft instantly dropping a
stern, had much ado blindly to struggle out from that frenzied twilight into the
clear air of day.
And now, abating in his flurry, the whale once more rolled out into view,
surging from side to side, spasmodically dilating and contracting his spout hole
with sharp, cracking, agonized respirations.
At last, gush after gush of clotted red gore, as if it had been the purple
leaves of red wine, shot into the frighted air, and falling back again,
ran dripping down his motionless flanks into the sea. His heart had burst.
"He is dead, Mr. Stub," said Tashego.
Yes. Both pipes smoked out, and withdrawing his own from his mouth,
Stubs scattered the dead ashes over the water, and for a moment stood
thoughtfully eyeing the vast corpse he had made.